Register of the Irwin T. and Shirley Holtzman collection, 1899-2010
Hoover Institution Archives
- Isaac Babel File, 1913-2002.
  - Collections, exhibitions, conferences, 1986-2000.; See also oversize and miscellaneous materials, box 148, for one item
    - Babel Centennial Conference, Gorky Institute, Moscow, 1994 June 6-9
      - Exhibition catalog (Folder 145: 5)
        (X.8).
      - Catalog for concurrent exhibition of materials from the Holtzman collection (Folder 145: 6)
        (X.9).
    - Isaac Emmanuilovich Babel Centenary Exhibition and Symposium, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, 1994 November 4-6. (Folder 145: 7)
      Invitation and program (X.10)
    - A Jew on Horseback: The Stories, Legacy and Fate of Isaac Babel, National Yiddish Book Center conference, 2000 December 1-3. (Folder 145: 8)
      Program and reading materials (X.11)
    - The Voice of Literature, New York, 2000 (Folder 145: 9)
      (X.12).
      Two programs for lecture series, including a tribute to Babel, at the 92nd Street Y Unterberg Poetry Center
  - Adaptations, 1963-2000.
    Monographs, poems, programs, and serial issues, relating to adaptations of Babel's works. Printed copies, unless otherwise noted
    - Ha-Shkiah, Tel Aviv, n.d. (Folder 145: 10)
      (XI.1).
      Hebrew translation of Babel's play, Zakat. Actor's script from Israeli production of play
    - Lessing, Doris, A Man and Two Women, New York, 1963 (Folder 145: 11)
      (XI.2).
      Includes the story, "An Homage for Isaac Babel"
    - Cohen, Arthur A., A Hero in His Time, Chicago, 1976 (Folder 145: 12)
      (XI.3).
      Novel with a dedication to Babel
    - Jewish Heritage Review, 1975 (Folder 145: 13)
      (XI.4).
      Contains mention of a posthumous award given to Babel
    - Edward M. Cohen, ed., New Jewish Voices: Plays Produced by the Jewish Repertory Theatre, Albany, 1985 (Folder 145: 14)
      (XI.5).
      Contains the play, "Benya the King," based on Babel's stories
    - TriQuarterly 58, 1983 Fall (Box-folder 146: 1)
      (XI.6).
      Contains a short story entitled "Isaac Babel"
    - Zhurbin, Aleksandr, Bindiuzhnik i Korol', Moscow, 1990 (Folder 146: 2)
      (XI.7).
      Musical score, with lyrics based on Babel's stories
    - "Babel's House, at Peredelkino," anonymous poem, 1991 (Folder 146: 3)
      (XI.8).
    - Mission statement and other materials, International Stanislavsky Theater Studio, Inc., Silver Spring, Maryland (Folder 146: 4)
      (XI.9).
      Includes information concerning Babel's grandson, Andrei Malaev-Babel
    - Skriabin, Mikhail and Leonard Garrilov, Svetit' mozhno – tol'ko sgoraia, Moscow, 1987 (Folder 146: 5)
      (XI.10).
      Printed copy of a novel in which Babel appears as a character
    - Stagebill, 1998 March (Folder 146: 6)
      (XI.11).
      Contains advertisement for a production of "City (Odessa Stories)," based on Babel's works
    - Fonseca, Rubem, Vast Emotions and Imperfect Thoughts, Hopewell, New Jersey (Folder 146: 7)
      (XI.12).
      English translation of Brazilian novel in which Babel and his work figure prominently. Folder also includes New York Times review of this book
    - Hirsch, Edward, "Reading Isaac Babel's Diary on the Lower East Side," TriQuarterly 107/108, 2000 Winter/Spring/Summer (Folder 146: 8)
      (XI.13).
      Photocopy of poem
  - Oversize and miscellaneous materials, 1921-2001 (Box 147)
    - Holograph certificate awarded to a soldier in the Soviet cavalry, 1921. (Folder 147: 1)
      Soldier served in the same unit as Babel
    - USSR in Construction. Soviet monthly produced in various languages
      - 1936 March (Folder 147: 2)
        (I.45).
        Text and pictorial supervision by Babel. Printed copy of English edition
      - 1937 April (Folder 147: 3-4)
        (I.46, I.47).
        Printed copies of Russian and German editions of a special issue devoted to Maxim Gorky. Contains editorial content attributed to Babel
    - Pervaia konnaia, Ogiz-Izogiz, 1938 (Folder 147: 5)
      (V.63).
      Album designed by Rodchenko and Stepanova to commemorate cavalry unit in which Babel had served
    - "Stories by Isaac Babel Read by Joseph Wiseman," New Rochelle, New York, 1966. (Folder 147: 6)
      One long-playing recording
    - One original caricature of Babel, by David Levine, 1969 (Box-folder 148: 1)
      (VII.22)
    - One photocopy of a pencil portrait of Babel, by Nathan Altman, 1927 (Folder 148: 2)
      (VII.23)
    - One photocopy of a pen and ink portrait of Babel, by Yuri Annenkov, 1925 (Folder 148: 3)
      (VII.25)
    - One original watercolor by Vitali Veksler, based on a theme from Babel's works, 1994 (Folder 148: 4)
      (VII.26)
    - One original poster for Babel Centennial Conference, Gorky Institute, Moscow, 1994 (Folder 148: 5)
    - One original watercolor by Avi Katz, based on a theme from 1920 Diary by Babel, 1995. (Folder 148: 6)
      Includes magazine reproduction of painting, 1995 October 5 (VII.27)
    - Remnick, David, "Isaac Babel's Tragedy," The New York Review of Books, 1997 April 10. (Folder 148: 7)
      Printed copy of complete serial issue
    - Gol'denberg, Mikhail, "Teper' mne zhit' ne zadut...,", 2001. (Folder 148: 8)
      Printed copy of a website article mentioning Babel
- Isaac Babel 2004 Increment File, 1929-2003.
  Printed matter arranged chronologically by title. Materials received in 2004
  - Printed matter, 1929-2003.
    Publications by or about Babel. Babel's name is omitted where he is the author
    - Red Cavalry, London, 1929 (Box-folder 161: 1)
    - L'armata a cavallo di Isacco Babel, Turin, 1932 (Folder 161: 2)
    - "Two Stories," Commentary, 1964 February (Folder 161: 3)
    - You Must Know Everything, New York, 1970 (Folder 161: 4)
    - "The Death of Dolgushov," in Irving Howe and Ilana Wiener Howe (eds.), Short Shorts: An Anthology of the Shortest Stories, 1982 (Folder 161: 5)
    - Freeborn, Richard, The Russian Revolutionary Novel: Turgenev to Pasternak, Cambridge, England, 1985 (Folder 161: 6)
    - "The King," in Jerome Charyn (ed.), The New Mystery, New York, 1993 (Box-folder 162: 1)
    - Collected Stories, London, 1998 (Folder 162: 2)
    - Odesskie rasskazy, Moscow, 2000 (Folder 162: 3)
    - Furst, Alan, Blood of Victory, New York, 2002 (Folder 162: 4)
    - Jansen, Marc and Nikita Petrov, Stalin's Loyal Executioner: People's Commisssar Nikolai Ezhov, 1895-1940, Stanford, California, 2002 (Box-folder 163: 1)
    - "Kol'tso Esfiri," Slovo/Word, nos. 35-36, 2002 (Folder 163: 2)
    - Parker, Jeff, "Babel Revisited: An Interview with Peter Constantine," Poets & Writers, 2002 November/December (Folder 163: 3)
    - Red Cavalry, New York, 2002 (Folder 163: 4)
    - Rosenstone, Robert A., King of Odessa, Evanston, Illinois, 2003 (Folder 163: 5)
- Incremental Materials (Folder 165-197)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu